<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Verified News Daily Briefing</title>
    <link>https://baghdadtomars.github.io/verified_news/</link>
    <description>A daily briefing on verified developments in science, health, the environment, technology, and global affairs.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 13:16:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>February 01, 2026</title>
      <description>The United States just recorded the largest single-year drop in murders in its history. In 2025, homicides fell by more than 20 percent compared to the year before. That is not a projection. That is not a goal. That is what happened.

The numbers tell a story of thousands of lives saved. In 2020 and 2021, at the height of the pandemic violence spike, the country recorded roughly 21,000 and 23,000 murders respectively. In 2025, that number fell to approximately 14,000. That means nearly 9,000 fewer people died from homicide last year compared to the peak.

The national murder rate dropped to about 4 per 100,000 people. That beats the previous historic low of 4.4 set in 2014. You have to go back to the 1950s to find numbers this low.

This was not isolated to one city or one region. Major cities across the country posted multi-decade lows simultaneously. Chicago ended 2025 with 416 homicides. That is the lowest number since 1965. In 2021, Chicago recorded 805 murders. The city cut that nearly in half in four years.

Philadelphia saw an even more dramatic shift. The city recorded 562 homicides in 2021, a record high. In 2025, that number dropped to 222. That is the lowest since 1966. A 52 percent reduction from the peak.

Detroit fell below 200 homicides for the first time since 1965. Baltimore recorded 133 murders, its lowest in nearly 50 years and a 58 percent drop over five years. Washington D.C. saw homicides fall 32 percent to 127, returning to levels not seen since the early 2010s.

New York City recorded about 303 murders, down 20 percent from the year before. December 2025 saw only 35 shooting incidents across the entire city. That was a record low, beating the previous benchmark from 2018 by 43 percent.

The decline extended beyond homicides. Carjackings, which became a symbol of pandemic-era crime, dropped 43 percent from 2024 and 61 percent from their 2023 peak. Non-fatal shootings fell 22 percent. Robberies dropped 23 percent.

Now, this success has limits. Domestic violence declined only 2 percent, showing that intimate partner violence operates differently from street violence and needs different interventions. Drug offenses actually increased. And nearly half of Americans still believe crime is rising nationally, even as the numbers tell the opposite story. Polling shows this perception gap is heavily influenced by political affiliation rather than actual experience with crime.

There is also concern about sustainability. Much of the investment in violence prevention came from federal pandemic relief funds that will expire in 2026. Cities may face difficult choices about whether to continue programs that contributed to these results.

But those concerns exist alongside genuine accomplishment. How did this happen? Researchers point to several factors working together.

First, the unique stressors of the pandemic subsided. In 2020 and 2021, schools closed. Courts shut down. Community centers went dark. The informal networks that keep neighborhoods stable disappeared almost overnight. By 2025, those institutions had fully returned. Schools operated normally. Courts cleared their backlogs. People returned to commuting, shopping, and socializing, restoring what researchers call natural surveillance in public spaces.

Second, federal investment through the American Rescue Plan funded community violence intervention programs at an unprecedented scale. Cities like Baltimore, Detroit, and Chicago hired violence interrupters and community mediators who worked directly with people at highest risk of shooting or being shot. In Baltimore, the Group Violence Reduction Strategy tracked specific results. More than 95 percent of participants were not victimized again. Nearly 98 percent did not commit new violent crimes.

Third, police departments shifted tactics. Instead of broad enforcement that alienated communities, many cities adopted precision policing. They focused on the small number of individuals actually driving violence rather than casting wide nets. In Washington D.C., federal prosecutors targeted specific crews running drug markets. After one takedown in the Kingman Park area, violent crime in that sector dropped 66 percent.

Fourth, the economy stabilized. Unemployment held between 4.4 and 4.6 percent. Inflation came down to about 2.7 percent. While the connection between economics and crime is complex, the absence of the mass unemployment seen in 2020 helped maintain social stability.

This was not just an American phenomenon. The United Kingdom saw parallel declines. London recorded its lowest homicide rate in over a decade. Homicides across England and Wales fell 6 to 7 percent. Knife crime dropped 9 percent. The synchronization across the Atlantic suggests that the pandemic disruption and subsequent recovery followed similar patterns in developed nations.

Chicago officials credit what they call a whole of government approach. Police, health departments, and housing agencies coordinated instead of working in isolation. The University of Chicago Crime Lab confirmed that shooting victims in the city fell by more than 33 percent, indicating fewer conflicts escalated to gunfire in the first place.

Detroit embedded prosecutors directly in police precincts, speeding the process from arrest to charging. The city invested pandemic relief funds in grassroots organizations that mediated disputes before they turned deadly. Carjackings there fell 46 percent.

The data comes from multiple independent sources that all point in the same direction. The Real-Time Crime Index tracks more than 500 police agencies covering 116 million people. The Council on Criminal Justice studies 35 to 40 major cities in depth. Local police departments publish daily and weekly dashboards. The preliminary FBI data aligns with all of these.

Homicide statistics are particularly reliable because, unlike property crimes that go unreported, every death produces a body and a coroner's report. The numbers cannot be hidden by changes in reporting behavior.

Experts do not expect another 20 percent drop in 2026. That velocity of decline is unusual. But the projection is for these gains to hold. The goal now shifts from crisis response to maintaining what has been built.

The year 2025 will be recorded as the year America reversed its pandemic crime surge. Thousands of people who would have died in earlier years are alive today. That is not optimism. That is arithmetic. The problem was real. The solution was real. And the results are measurable in lives saved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://baghdadtomars.github.io/verified_news/audio/briefing_01-02-2026_14-13-53.wav</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://baghdadtomars.github.io/verified_news/audio/briefing_01-02-2026_14-13-53.wav" length="84776332" type="audio/wav"/>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 13:16:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>February 01, 2026</title>
      <description>This is a test story for the RSS feed verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://baghdadtomars.github.io/verified_news/audio/test_briefing.wav</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://baghdadtomars.github.io/verified_news/audio/test_briefing.wav" length="28" type="audio/wav"/>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 12:28:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
